<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.artbrock.com/assets/xslt/rss.xslt" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://www.artbrock.com/assets/css/rss.css" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Arthur Brock's Personal Site</title>
		<description>Culture-Hacking, Alt.Education, Targeted Currency Design, NextNet Technologies.</description>
		<link>https://www.artbrock.com/</link>
		<atom:link href="https://www.artbrock.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>But Data Doesn't Exist</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/07/11/but-data-doesnt-exist</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 01:17:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;true-fallacies-of-distributed-computing&quot;&gt;True Fallacies of Distributed Computing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a wikipedia article about the fallacies of distributed computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-exists&quot;&gt;Data Exists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having pretty tight control of a computing space allows people to maintain the illusion that data “exists.” But if we tell the truth, forces outside the control of your program disrupt data on a regular basis (buffer overruns, memory errors, seg faults, drive failures, power surges, solar flares?, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we expand computing outside the bounds of a single computer these disruptions become so frequent that it we perform extremely awkward gyrations to preserve the illusion of data integrity (checksums, cryptographic hashes, signatures, consensus, leader election strategies for resolving inevitable differences, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem that data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is not stateful, it is interactive process. We resolve the quantum superpositions of probabilities only by interacting with something, and it is the AGENCY involved in that process of interaction that determines/reports/creates information or data. To divorce that data from the agency which produced it and act like it “exists” as some kind of truth is to create a fiction which we confuse with reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All data comes into existence through a process of authorship by some agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sales figures are reported by someone (they may have reasons to inflate them).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The temperature is measured by some device (it may not be well placed or calibrated)
 -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-exists&quot;&gt;Time Exists&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/07/11/but-data-doesnt-exist</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A major phase shift</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/06/12/phase-shift</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2017 21:11:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably seen a lot more activity around the MetaCurrency Project in recent months: a new Ceptr web site, Ceptr broken down into clearer sub-projects, blockchain alternatives, lots of code releases, Hackathons, virtual potlucks, online presentations, etc. I guess we ought to make it clearer what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time we’ve operated as one of those fringy open source projects like some mad scientists experimenting in their garage. But now we must navigate the transition from a tech hobby project to a scalable business, in part, because we’ve been approached by funders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our focus is initially on Holochain, a scalable blockchain alternative which is part of the larger Ceptr social OS. Watch for updates on the &lt;a href=&quot;/ceptr/blog&quot;&gt;Ceptr blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ceptr.org/images/chrysalis_butterfly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Transformation&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-now&quot;&gt;Why now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, &lt;strong&gt;timing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a window of opportunity that simply wasn’t here a year ago. Far more people are ready to understand what we’re building. Blockchain has become quite the rage, so people are trying to solve all sorts of centralization problems with it. Global consensus on local independent actions as (as in the architecture of blockchain) will never scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don’t provide a better alternative before people sour on blockchain limitations, people may not be willing to listen to how our architecture is different if blockchain becomes perceived as a dead-end for large scale data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other reason is &lt;strong&gt;money&lt;/strong&gt;. Once others started realizing they need the tools we’re building for the things they want to build, they started approaching us to see if funding would get it for them faster. In response, we came up with a great structure for accepting investment, so they have extraordinary opportunities for big upsides, while we preserve the integrity of our commitment to open source resources for all humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just got our initial funds in the door in last weeks. So you’ll see us ramping up our business ecosystem, running new internship/residency programs, and launching more server infrastructure, and implementing ways of tracking the value that people contribute to the project ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Active team members doubled in the last few months (from 6 to 12), and we expect it to double again this summer, and likely again in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-deck-in-tech&quot;&gt;On Deck in Tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our core code provides a more stable foundation for the next layers of features, you can expect to see a lot more happening, much more quickly. Here’s what we expect to complete this summer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alpha release of Holochain&lt;/strong&gt; after our current security milestone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holochain App Generator&lt;/strong&gt; which walks you through the process of building a distributed app on holochain and generates most of the schemas, code, and files for you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large-Scale Multi-Node Test Rig&lt;/strong&gt; - container automation and testing for scalability of your application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core Holochain Services&lt;/strong&gt; - This summer we’re building a series of holochain apps to expose critical core services distributed to other apps, so you don’t have to build these things yourself.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holochain Package Manager&lt;/strong&gt; - a compact runtime distribution of holochain which comes with the one app which lets you install whatever other apps people want to publish on this distributed package management system.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DPKI&lt;/strong&gt; (Distributed Public Key Infrastructure) - sophisticated services for key management, revocation, and identity validation where you can control and own your own data.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HC Index&lt;/strong&gt; - pluggable index services to make it easier to find things scattered across an application’s DHT space.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pluggable Governance&lt;/strong&gt; - a variety of options for integrating decision-making for evolving the code of holochain apps&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HC Cache&lt;/strong&gt; - smart caching services to enable your application to automatically have CDN-like (content delivery network) performance.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve gotten to this transition point because a bunch of people have been putting in good work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding:&lt;/strong&gt; A shout-out to Ferananda Ibarra and Jeff Clearwater, of &lt;a href=&quot;/village-lab&quot;&gt;Village Lab&lt;/a&gt;, who have been developing the Wealth Stewardship Circle model for generating and stewarding collective wealth which transcends the investor/philanthropist box to weave healthier dynamics. Much of our funding has been been attracted through their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dev:&lt;/strong&gt; Our software development on holochain has been steadily increasing. &lt;a href=&quot;/github/dayzee&quot;&gt;DayZee&lt;/a&gt; has been improving our docker containers especially for multi-node testing of our P2P gossip protocols. &lt;a href=&quot;/github/timotree3&quot;&gt;Timotree3&lt;/a&gt; has been cleaning up loose ends in a bunch of areas, from docker container optimization, and cross-platform scripting, to tightening up security of stray exposed variables and functions. &lt;a href=&quot;/github/neonphog&quot;&gt;Neonphog&lt;/a&gt; is building our holochain app scaffolding system and app wizard to make it fast and easy to produce the basics of a holochain app instantly. &lt;a href=&quot;/github/luckus&quot;&gt;Lucksus&lt;/a&gt; has come over from Germany to dive deep with &lt;a href=&quot;/github/zippy&quot;&gt;Zippy&lt;/a&gt; on holochain core, internal message flows, and our security implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biz:&lt;/strong&gt; Currently our fastest area of growth has been in the domain of growing our business infrastructure. Mary Camacho has started bringing some much needed leadership to augment Arthur in this domain. Matthew Schutte has invested significant work into creating a work and live space for our &lt;a href=&quot;/ceptr/residency&quot;&gt;summer residency program&lt;/a&gt;. Jarod Holtz has essentially taken on full-time administration and support functions for Arthur, Mary, Matthew, Ferananda which amplifies everyone’s results. Also, a secret team with more new leadership has assembled to explore options related to doing an ICO for our next major phase of development.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/06/12/phase-shift</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Commons Engine</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/06/05/commons-engine</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 03:16:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;commons-engine&quot;&gt;Commons Engine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We intend to turn the management of Ceptr and its software ecosystem over to a Sovereign Accountable Commons (our counterpart to a DAO - decentralized autonomous organization). For us this means building:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sophisticated value accounting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commons-based asset management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A cryptocurrency for purchase (and pre-purchase of assets)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrated/pluggable governance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royalties &amp;amp; Rewards (What if you earned royalties on code (or other assets) you shared.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we have to build these things for ourselves, we will also share them as a tool for launching platform cooperatives (think Uber without an extractive corporation in the middle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expect to see more about this, our new partnerships in the space, and maybe even a crowdfunding campaign to help get it launched.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/06/05/commons-engine</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Intro to Currency Design</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/27/intro-to-currency-design</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:19:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;ferananda&quot;&gt;Ferananda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if there was a currency that could be used to enslave you, without you even realizing it? Wouldn’t you want to know? Wouldn’t you want to learn to see how it works? How it does that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guess what? That’s how the existing monetary system works because of rules that are invisible to most of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All currencies operate at two levels. There the level of the tokens – how they’re earned or exchanged, and then level of the currency system itself – what patterns are forged by its rules… rules on both levels. Some of the rules are visible to everybody, and some of them are hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monopoly game example: Jesus, Buddha, Gandhi, enlightened people… the same outcome. One of them takes everything from everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is that outcome written into the rules? Each person just takes their turn, rolls the dice, lands on a square, buys properties, charges people to stay at their property…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the rules at the level of tokens and players, but what are “social physics” they create? The forces, as reliable as gravity, that are at play…										
In this video, we want to: 1) show you the two levels that currencies operate on, 2) how to see the rules and patterns on each level, and hopefully, 3) awaken the currency designer in you with the capability to build currencies that help build a world we all want to live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arthur&quot;&gt;Arthur&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to start by expanding our understanding of “CURRENCY” to be something much bigger and more powerful than “money.”
We already know money is powerful, but if you truly understand how we’re using the word currency, you’ll have access to something even bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes…. I know that in everyday English those two words are used pretty interchangeably, but even if just for this video, I invite you to try on a new perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to warn you. This is one of those Red Pill / Blue Pill moments that once you’ve been able to see the matrix, you may not easily be able to go back from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, lets say currencies are symbol systems we create to manage currents or flows.– Money, which we use to manage flows of goods and services is just a small part of the landscape of currencies.										
Of course, we also use other kinds of currencies… Reputation currencies like credit ratings or college degrees, Measurement currencies like grades in school, certified Organic, or Fair trade. And a wide range of niche currencies for shaping specific flows like even.							
This may sound like I’m mixing together a lot of different things, but that’s because there truly are lots of different currencies. Hopefully it will soon be clear what is and what isn’t a currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look more carefully at some of examples of currencies which are not money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;College degrees&lt;/strong&gt; are a reputation currency which we’re led to believe you need to get good job. But let’s closer at how you get a college degree?
Well, you need to fulfill the degree requirements which means 12 credits of this thing, 15 credits of that thing, and 25 credits in another category. The &lt;strong&gt;Credits&lt;/strong&gt; are a unit of account currency just counting the number of course hours you have in different categories.
But the credits only count if you get good enough &lt;strong&gt;grades&lt;/strong&gt;. Grades are a performance metric currency… designed to measure how well you’re learning the content of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, these three non-monetary currencies shape the behavior of millions of students. These currencies are even used to divide up power within the school, with the university issuing the degree, departments issuing credits and professors issuing grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an interesting little example in here… &lt;strong&gt;Tutors:&lt;/strong&gt; Why would you pay for a tutor to teach you something when you’re already paying a university to teach it to you? Grades. Grades create the market for tutors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Olympic medals&lt;/strong&gt; shape behavior of millions of athletes all over the world competing to be recognized as the best. And its certainly not because of the monetary value of the gold or silver or bronze plating on the medal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ratings:&lt;/strong&gt; Ebay beat out other online auctions sites because it created a reputation currency. The reputation currency started being necessary to sell big ticket items.	 People turn to Amazon for product ratings, Yelp for restaurant ratings, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pedigrees:&lt;/strong&gt; Purebred Dogs with a pedigree sell for more in the marketplace. In some places, humans with the right pedigree are called royalty, get immense power and/or wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whoa! It seems even NON-monetary currencies effect monetary power, control, and create markets. 										
What other kinds of power might they have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As individuals, unsurprisingly we tend to focus a lot on the level of individuals and how we’re doing in the game compared to other individuals. This can make it hard to see how currencies shape patterns at much larger levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we tell a story about evolution that places us at the top of an evolutionary ladder as the pinnacle of evolutionary achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story fails to recognize how evolution builds new levels of complexity out of prior successes. The green algae that mastered photosynthesis is now built into the DNA of every plant, and is exactly what makes them have green leaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like that algae got built into the cells of plants, we have become cells in larger social organisms like corporations, governments, and institutions…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes.. organisms… with their own patterns of behavior and intelligence distinct from our own as individuals.  They seek self-preservation, can spin off offspring, and have a pattern of existence that continues even as cells(people) within it are replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is hard for us to see for a few reasons. 1) We don’t like to think of ourselves as cells in an organism. and 2) because we’re not used to differentiating between the aggregate behavior of individuals, and individuals whose behavior has become organ-ized by a larger organ-ism. But this is definitely organized behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you were hanging out with some friends and said: “Hey, I know what we should do this evening. Let’s go dig for coal!” (said nobody ever). The behavior of digging for coal, and many more, happen not so much from individual choice, but from operating in the “body” of a social organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nervous system, feedback loops, and “intelligence” of these corporate bodies… all run on currencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to change the behavior of a corporation and all the people in it, all you have to do is change its currencies.  It will immediately start to optimize itself to new incentives. Everything else ripples out from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what this looks like…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ferananda-1&quot;&gt;Ferananda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You go to the DMV to get a drivers license. Even though you might be able to prove to a person behind the counter that you can drive, they won’t give you a license without a special kind of currency.										
You need a birth certificate, passport, or license from another state. 										
Even though the human your interacting with can obviously see you, the state cannot. The State “sees” your existence by virtue of those forms identifying currencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know humans are born and that they die, but as far as the nervous system of the social organisms of the State is concerned, humans are issued through birth certificates, and expired through death certs.										
Sounds crazy? Try to get someone at a bank or IRS to interact with you without your Tax ID# / SSN…!!										
Maybe now you can understand how we’re using the word currency. Think of it as “Current-See.” A symbol system for making particular currents or flows visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t really interact with something if we can’t “see” it. Social organisms can only “see” the world through current-sees. Decisions are made based on these. Just think of the government, if they can’t measure it, they can’t see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do these currencies work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arthur-1&quot;&gt;Arthur&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to the two levels. 1) The currency tokens or symbols themselves. 2) The system which establishes and maintains the rules for the curreny tokens. 										
Each of these levels follow a specific pattern. Knowing what’s involved with these patterns is one of your tickets in to SEE forces controlling the players and plays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Currency Token Life Cycle: Rules for a) Issuance b) Transaction c) Interplay with other currencies d) Expiration, Redemption, Retiremernt										
&lt;strong&gt;Issuance:&lt;/strong&gt; Who gets to create the tokens and how? Are they fiat (spoken into being from nothing .. like dollars and bitcoins)? Are they created as they are backed by something of value? Are they mutual credit (created via extending credit to each other via double-entry accounting)?									
&lt;strong&gt;Transaction:&lt;/strong&gt; Can be be traded? How are transactions structured? Who can transact? Special triggers? Limits? Are there tax conseqeunces? What accounting methods? Transaction fees… interest-bearing									
&lt;strong&gt;Interplay:&lt;/strong&gt; Are there dependencies on other currencies? (grades and credits to get a degree. HS to get into College) Dependent on others? Other dependent on this? Conversions? Thresholds?									
&lt;strong&gt;Retirement:&lt;/strong&gt; How are units of the currency retired/redeemed/expired? Expiration of flyer miles. Revokation of college credits, gades or degrees. Redemptoin in backed currencies									
When you know the life cycle of currency tokens you can identify the rules that govern each phase to grasp the dynamics of the whole cycle.										
Everyone can create value, but if you make it illegal for any but a small group to create money (counterfeiting), you can use that ability to issue money, to control the everyone’s value										
Take dollars for example, most people only know the rules for the transaction phase. They don’t know who issues them (bankers) or how (as loans and accounting for deposits as asset not lability). Or realize when you pay back principle on a loan, those dollars are being retired. Or that the cash sitting in a bank’s vault is actually not in circulation… It is parked in limbo, under the bank’s guardianship, but not under their ownership. Credit ratings effecting cost and avalability of money, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ferananda-2&quot;&gt;Ferananda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously the currency token rules establish certain patterns of power by saying how they are created, used, and destroyed, but there’s hidden power behind all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Currency SYSTEM Life Cycle: Who decides the rules of the game? How are they reviewed, changed, or perpetuated? See diagram										
&lt;strong&gt;Roots:&lt;/strong&gt; What are the origins of the system? Who conceived, designed, or built it? All currencies have historical and political origins. What agenda was it designed to serve? For whom?									
&lt;strong&gt;Operation:&lt;/strong&gt; Who manages the system? Oversees its changes? Evaluates its success?  How do they do these things? Through what entities or mechanisms?									
&lt;strong&gt;Evolution:&lt;/strong&gt; Who decides what needs to change? Implements those changes? Enforces adoption or compliance? Through what entities or mechanisms?									
&lt;strong&gt;Governance:&lt;/strong&gt; Is there a group who exerts signicant control or influence over the Managers, Change-makers, Enforcers, or Evaluators even if they are not actively in those roles?									
&lt;strong&gt;Closure:&lt;/strong&gt; Is there a plan for end-of-life of the currency system? Winding it down? 									
You may have already figured this out, but it is worth making explicit, the people in the role of governance at the system level, essentially control the dynamics on both levels.										
Given most people aren’t aware of much beyond the transaction domain on the token level, most folks need to dig a lot deeper to see the full spectrum of currency dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;art&quot;&gt;Art&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we go even deeper, let’s look at some currency innovations, and their blind spots, to see why this matters so much.										
Community Currencies: Most community currencies express an economic ideology of a small group in the governance role. They may object to centralized issuance and opt for mutual credit. Or they don’t like debt, and do a value backed scheme. Or they don’t like the growth imperative which comes from issuing all money as debt which bears interest. Occasionally, someone will swing way out there and set a value reference to hours and maybe even remove pricing (1 hr = 1 hr).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies: Most cryptocurrencies encode a monetary function as envisioned by an individual or small group in the governance role. They typically object to centralized issuance by fiat, choosing instead to implement semi-randomized issuance by fiat using a PoW or PoS. They also implement transparent accounting on a blockchain, which they consider decentralized because there is not one master copy, everyone that can afford the cost of the hardware has a full copy of the whole economy.										
If you look at a large scope of hundreds of design choices, most of these currencies are stuck on just a few variables (mostly about issuance) at the Token level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They duplicate the artificial scarcity of interest with requiring massive compute power for PoW. They duplicate the currency being locked into a growth trajectory, of pre-ordained design. and Without decentralized governance of the rules of the currency (or the versioning of software in a digital currency), is a currency actually decentralized?										
These systems are stuck in a monetary frame, completely missing the boat on Current-Sees as nervous systems of social organisms.										
So… how do we go beyond the monetary frame?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fer&quot;&gt;Fer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To open our vision a little wider let’s look a “wealth.” Just as we expanded our perception of currency, we need to expand our understanding of wealth.										
We typically think of wealth as accumulating lots of riches. 					But Wealth is not about accumulation – any more than health is about maximizing your weight					
Wealth is about capacity: To move things to where they’re needed. To solve problems. To provide for a quality of life or experience. The resilience to adapt to change.										
Wealth isn’t an individual bank balance, it is the collective configuration which enables healthy patterns of flow. It is truly COMMONwealth.										
Think about it as economic health. Your health is not about having massive stockpiles of calories, but strength, speed, flexibility, resilience to adverse circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;art-1&quot;&gt;Art&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every living system, whether a cell, a human, an ecosystem, a corporation, or an economy has particular dimensions thru which we can see patterns of flow.										
These different dimensions use different type of currencies as signaling systems for maintaining healthy patterns of flow.										
Separate from the living system is the speculative economy… the gambling market about the living systems. We’ve mistaken those gambling chips, like dollars, for real wealth.										
Let’s look at currencies which connect in with the feedback loops in each dimension… like commodities, goods, or services in the parts and products layer. Various measurements and metrics in the properties layer.										
… Rankings at the performance layer, and Names, Titles, Certifications at the relational layer. We’re not going to dive in too deep in this video. We’ll get into that in our currency design webinar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to share a few last things to clear up some common sources of confusion. When people first try to expand their vision of currencies and wealth they start to think we’re saying: 										
“Everything is a currency!” Flows of value, love, time, attention, sharing, caring, etc… No! Those are flows. We use currencies to help shape healthy patterns of those flows.										
It’s a map vs. territory thing. Currencies are symbols. they are information about flows. Your college degree is just an indication about some learning, it is not the learning itself.										
You might use page hits to measure attention, but page hits are not attention. You might use Olympic medals to rank athletes, but they just point to athletic skill, they are not the skills.										
The title “President of the US” points to a bunch of relationships and power dynamics, but it is not those relationships. 										
Money flows in the opposite direction of value, it is not the value itself, just a marker of the value that moves the opposite direction.										
Maps are extremely useful ! Especially when we want to arrange or coordinate collective behavior. But they are not the territory. 										
But unlike a paper map which is an object, currency tokens also flow, so they create living maps that we are always responding to and interacting with.										
So what kind of wealth or capacites are you trying to create? And what kind of living map will enable people to orchestrate themselves into that healthy pattern?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ferananda-3&quot;&gt;Ferananda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that this has cracked open new possibilities and perspectives on the power of currencies…										
…and specifically how currencies shape the capacities of social organisms like corporations and economies, because the patterns we’ve been using are wreaking some havoc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check our web site for more helpful resources. In particular, we are offering some online webinars to dive deep into this stuff.										
There are three different series or tracks: 										
One for monetary design and cryptocurrencies.									
Another for going beyond sustainability into deisigning for thrivability.									
The third is for building community, doing culture-hacking, designing social flows.									
Speak about us been open to different possibilities for investment  - 50% money - 50% open to other forms of contribution that can be measured									
Check it out at MetaCurrency.org&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for listening. And here’s to your wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/27/intro-to-currency-design</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Powerful Design Principles for Next-Gen Governance</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/12/powerful-design-principles-for-next-gen-governance</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 03:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/02/11/challenging-broken-assumptions-of-governance&quot;&gt;my last post&lt;/a&gt;, I deconstructed a number of core assumptions that we tend to take for granted as true, and that most of our tools of governance are built around. I didn’t mean to just stop there without getting to the good news, but the post was getting long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If things we’re used to leaning on to organize ourselves don’t work, what can we count on? Let’s establish some powerful principles to work from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;baseline-governance-is-for-and-by-humans&quot;&gt;Baseline: Governance is for and by Humans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just tell the truth about ourselves as humans. We’re not perfect. We’re not rational. We even often have conflicting beliefs, desires and commitments. We’re kind of a mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, most of us imagine ourselves as on less messy end of that spectrum, and stare slack-jawed at the craziness of others. Yet, there are others looking at us that way on occasion too. So, let’s be clear, governance for people who are a mess will be messy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think I’m going to provide some neat and tidy, mathematical, mechanistic, or computational solution for the perfect model of governance, than I’m pretty sure you haven’t been tracking my work. I’m never about ONE way of doing things, but favor having the adaptive capacity to choose between a number of ways as circumstances require.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that might sound complicated, actually, it’s beyond complicated it’s complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any system of governance that does not work well FOR people will  If you think machines are going to solve the problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think arriving at an answer which an algorithm says is best, but doesn’t feel right to people…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;baseline-governance-is-for-and-by-humans-1&quot;&gt;Baseline: Governance is for and by Humans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’re messy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Governance will be messy too&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am not going to propose a tidy solution, because the way we need to operate with the world is too complex for any prefabricated structure (including our Constitution).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cynefin quadrants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cynefin S curves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guidelines-and-principles&quot;&gt;Guidelines and Principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-selection-and-levels-of-participation&quot;&gt;Self-Selection and Levels of Participation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pull Not Push
signal/noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-alignment-before-agreement&quot;&gt;Building Alignment before Agreement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feelings-are-as-valid-as-reason&quot;&gt;Feelings are as valid as Reason&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Values before Facts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimize-for-wisdom&quot;&gt;Optimize for Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decisions are not in isolation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimize-for-agency&quot;&gt;Optimize for Agency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cascading Logarithmic Proxies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fail-fast-then-iterate&quot;&gt;Fail Fast then Iterate!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Context &amp;amp; Culture (for trans)
Awareness(Values/Reason/Intent)/Protocol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objections&quot;&gt;Objections:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;youre-just-a-techno-utopian&quot;&gt;You’re just a techno-utopian!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, yeah… If you need to throw some label on my to invalidate what I’m saying rather than consider it, do what you must. You might want to check if you’re blindly clinging to &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/02/11/challenging-broken-assumptions-of-governance&quot;&gt;assumptions about governance that are simply not true&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think technology will magically solve our problems. PEOPLE have to do that work. Remember, language and currencies are technologies we use every day to coordinate on massive scales, just like DNA is a technology our cells use to coordinate on massive scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve got to use the right tools for the job. In the case of P2P governance, some of those are new computing and cryptographic technologies. It’s probably a good idea to get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-oversimplified&quot;&gt;It’s Oversimplified&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an introductory article. For most people reading it, these ideas and approaches are novel and probably seem complex. Please don’t assume that because I don’t drill into great detail about every piece, that there are no supporting details. I’d invite you into the inquiry with me about those tangible details, just because I have some, doesn’t mean they’re right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-too-complicated--youll-never-get-people-on-board&quot;&gt;It’s too Complicated / You’ll never get people on board&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When our current system comes down, they’ll have to choose something to believe in. Let’s look at some indicators of how hard it would be to get people onboard for something like this, using Moore’s model of crossing the chasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;crossing-the-chasm--distributed-tech&quot;&gt;Crossing the chasm – distributed tech&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;78% of the US Population are active Facebook users. That is a much higher level of participation than happens in government, even just voting, even in controversial presidential election years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;100 million bitcoin users not to mention other blockchain tech. Billions going into it this year. Banks… etc. Decentralized crypto systems have reached mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-you-get-to-decide-the-algorithms&quot;&gt;So you get to decide the algorithms?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. You do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me the point of this approach is not to establish some new technocracy where the geeks rule the world through their manipulation of the technology everyone uses for decision-making. Replacing the current banksters with geeksters won’t really solve our problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this is why I’ve spent much of the past decade designing and building decentralized, uncorruptable architectures with no dependancies on centralized services of any kind. This is our greatest protection from corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;target-alignment-before-agreement&quot;&gt;Target Alignment before Agreement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimize-for-wisdom-1&quot;&gt;Optimize for Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much of political theory is about POWER. Checks and balances to prevent its abuse. How to seize it. How to hold it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;concentrations of power, wealth, information&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pull-not-push&quot;&gt;Pull Not Push&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not about pushing your voice, but pulling who’s input we really need for good decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimize-for-agency-1&quot;&gt;Optimize for Agency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;culture&quot;&gt;Culture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cascading-logarithmic-proxies&quot;&gt;Cascading Logarithmic Proxies&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/12/powerful-design-principles-for-next-gen-governance</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Challenging Broken Assumptions of Governance</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/11/challenging-broken-assumptions-of-governance</link>
				<pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 04:30:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;broken-assumptions-of-governance&quot;&gt;Broken Assumptions of Governance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;!-- TOC START min:1 max:3 link:true update:true --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#broken-assumptions-of-governance&quot;&gt;Broken Assumptions of Governance&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#lets-get-real&quot;&gt;Let’s Get Real&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#people-make-rational-decisions&quot;&gt;People Make Rational Decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#people-follow-procedures&quot;&gt;People Follow Procedures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#governance-should-treat-everyone-equally&quot;&gt;Governance Should Treat Everyone Equally&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#voting-works&quot;&gt;Voting Works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#we-can-have-more-parties--elect-better-representatives&quot;&gt;We Can Have more Parties / Elect Better Representatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#we-know-what-decisions-to-make&quot;&gt;We Know What Decisions To Make&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#laws-should-be-carefully-deliberated-and-made-to-last&quot;&gt;Laws Should Be Carefully Deliberated and Made to Last&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#transparency-blockchain-will-save-us&quot;&gt;Transparency (Blockchain Will Save Us)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#so-is-there-no-hope&quot;&gt;So, Is There No Hope?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- TOC END --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I challenge a lot of sacred cows about governance here. If you’ve been working or building something in that space, you may find this article disturbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Before you post an angry comment, please know that I recognize the commitments behind these assumptions as beautiful and maybe even something to strive for, but it doesn’t make them true. Also, in an effort to keep this short, a handful of sentences will not “prove” anything beyond a doubt. Just see if you can consider a larger possibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe we need to do a reset, and stop limiting next-gen governance by the tools and assumptions of our past approaches. To meet the huge challenges confronting us, we need more than incremental digital tweaks, we need a breakthrough in large-scale collective wisdom. I hope to provide a sense of how that is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-get-real&quot;&gt;Let’s Get Real&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your primary experience with governance is the morass of gridlock and corruption that passes for politics today, you’d be justified in being dismissive of ungrounded theories  However, if you are willing to consider the things I point out in this post, you might discover that it’s our CURRENT models and practices of governance that fail to be grounded in reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have experienced a wide gamut of approaches and settings for governance ranging from do-acracy, adhocracy, sociocracy, corporate hierarchies of some of the largest companies, bureaucracies of the educational system, egomaniacal tyrants, churches and religious societies, agile start-ups, anarchy, Quaker communities, hippy ecovillages, political organizing and activism, Occupy Wall Street assemblies, benificent dictators, online communities, and schools run by kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying I’m the expert, I’m just saying I’ve tried a lot of things, gotten my hands dirty, and experienced some stuff that works. I’ve also observed a lot of stuff that doesn’t work, or at least where the measure of working pales in comparison to the effectiveness of things that actually do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter what brilliant ancient or modern political philosopher set forth the ideals we’ve followed, if we build next-gen solutions on broken assumptions, we’ll stay stuck patterns of dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s shake up some of our assumptions about governance we mostly take for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;people-make-rational-decisions&quot;&gt;People Make Rational Decisions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, but we don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/wired/decision-making&quot;&gt;Neurologically speaking&lt;/a&gt;, the ability to decide is an emotional capacity. The rational weighing of pros and cons continues ad infinitum without the emotional will to bring it to closure and act. But that’s just the tip of the iceberg of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180+_biases,_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_(jm3).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cognitive biases&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to oversimplify issues for people to understand them. Our reasoning is impaired by hundreds of cognitive biases. We say and do things to be accepted by our peers and groups, and let our need for acceptance or preoccupation with immediate desires overshadow our ability to perceive things rationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been perfecting the manipulation of people using human irrationality for many decades. Advertising firms use it to make you buy junk. Political campaigns use it to alienate you from opponents, or mobilize people with angering ballot initiatives. The Trump campaign leverages your social media activity and uses it for fine-tuned, &lt;a href=&quot;/vice/cambridge-analytica&quot;&gt;fully individualized manipulation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governance which relies on the notion that people are inclined to make rational decisions falls victim to our own frailties. However, since we know about our limitations, we could incorporate them into good designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;people-follow-procedures&quot;&gt;People Follow Procedures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, it’s possible to create social processes which help keep our irrationality in check. For example, models like Holocracy, have you speak from a role or responsibility that you have, rather than from your personal beliefs or preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good social processes are compelling and following them can become deeply embedded into the culture of a group. However, humans aren’t robots, and the more contrived, structured, and rational you make a process, the less people tend to enjoy or adhere to it. If the conversation is limited only to rational discourse, people don’t end up &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt; heard, seen, or acknowledged. Even the most rational among us need not only to speak, but to FEEL heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when people mostly follow a procedure, they won’t follow it consistently. We all agree driving on the correct side of the road is important, yet we bend that rule when we think circumstances warrant it. When people know the system is preventing them from doing what the feel is right, they find ways to get around the system, even when they agree with most of its workings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will &lt;a href=&quot;wp def&quot;&gt;Smart Contracts&lt;/a&gt; solve this? Not really. The art of next-gen governance design isn’t to automate away all choices, but provide support (via technical process, social process, or physical structures) for parts where tend to be most irrational. Yet include ways that people can exercise choice (opt-in, opt-out, or work-around) in places where human judgment tends to be as good or better than prefab designs. Humans won’t just follow software anyway, we demand an emotional experience of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;governance-should-treat-everyone-equally&quot;&gt;Governance Should Treat Everyone Equally&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not equal. We have differences – interests, attention spans, beliefs, expectations, strengths, weaknesses, skills, habits, languages, etc. The real goal is to be treated equitably and fairly, not as identical interchangeable units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an era of massive customization – of media, products, art, and experiences – why should we be stuck with one-size-fits-all governance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the game wasn’t just “one person, one vote” which is rooted in equalizing the power of your vote or your voice, but was instead about finding the highest wisdom or best path? To achieve that, we might have to recognize different people bring different skills, knowledge, competencies, and figure out how to optimize everyone’s unique contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some modern tools make good steps in this direction. Direct democracy, enables people to participate directly in discussion and voting on individual issues rather than isolating everyone from direct participation through representatives. Liquid democracy enables people to delegate their votes to people based on specific topics or domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this is touchy subject likely to trigger people’s fears of elitism or abuse of power, but I am convinced that it is possible to responsibly wield tools like the &lt;a href=&quot;/vice/cambridge-analytica&quot;&gt;extreme targeting used in Trump’s campaign&lt;/a&gt; not to manipulate people, but to optimize participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your “governance feed” becomes tailored to your interests, attention span, ways you like to contribute or participate. You could also be directly tagged by a friend or colleague to bring something to your attention that might not fit your typical interests. We might be able to keep governance fun and call out the best in people – but not if can’t include difference and must pretend equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is someone more or less important because they choose to participate in environmental decisions instead health care or communications?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;voting-works&quot;&gt;Voting Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, voting mostly sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It reduces rich, nuanced discourse to one dimensional sums of numbers. Even if you use more advanced runoff techniques or pairwise comparison algorithms, you basically reduce issues to a popularity contest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I sometimes use voting, but it is important to know that popularity is not wisdom. Just because something is currently popular doesn’t make it good or wise. Knowing how popular something is can be extremely useful, especially for understanding paths to adoption, but aren’t their better ways of making good decisions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But you can’t have democracy without voting!” – Not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from my experience, every setting where voting was used to decide things was less satisfying (in terms of quality of decisions, experience of participation, and belief you could effect needed changes) than groups where the process for discourse went deep enough that alignment was clear without a need for counting votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is still “rule by the people” (democracy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-can-have-more-parties--elect-better-representatives&quot;&gt;We Can Have more Parties / Elect Better Representatives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flex-video youtube widescreen&quot; style=&quot;height: px; width: 100%; background: black;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5tu32CCA_Ig&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting aside the fact that concentrating power into the hands of a small number of representatives makes it easy for the wealthy to target their influence and manipulate those “representatives.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representatives can’t represent us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least not in the general sense, that across all issues someone who doesn’t even know me could be said to represent my perspective or interest in: net neutrality, military spending, drug enforcement, funding for arts, immigration policy, etc. On a specific issue, I certainly might say: “Hey, the things that person is saying really represent what I think about that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that kind of delegation of narrow representation may be feasible, like in liquid democracy. But what about this concentrating of power effect? Doesn’t it still warp outcomes? &lt;a href=&quot;Something I've written&quot;&gt;Yes it does&lt;/a&gt;. Ideally, the more power becomes aggregated or concentrated, a system ends up with poorer discourse and is easier to manipulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-know-what-decisions-to-make&quot;&gt;We Know What Decisions To Make&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might have been much easier to address sustainable energy use or C02 emissions if we designed all our technology with that in mind from the beginning. But we didn’t yet know it mattered. And now that we’re addicted to convenience and certain lifestyles, it’s much harder to change course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the deeper problem is that decisions are discrete, but the world is wholly interconnected. When me make a decision, we &lt;a href=&quot;/etym/decide&quot;&gt;cut off&lt;/a&gt; a scope of reality that we’re considering, and what we think could make it work better (who to date, a better job, a CO2 policy, use of resources on state lands)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we cut out that little segment of reality, we did using a bunch of assumptions about how things work, and beliefs about how they are separate or independent of each other. Unfortunately, this is already a faulty model. Everything is connected, but our decision making processes can’t deal with the complexity of “everything.” So we chop the world into arbitrary parts and convince ourselves our cutting, and our understanding of that segment is good enough to make useful decisions about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chances are good, that we’re fooling ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;laws-should-be-carefully-deliberated-and-made-to-last&quot;&gt;Laws Should Be Carefully Deliberated and Made to Last&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve taken some piece of the world that we’re going to make a decision about (funding for head start programs, health care insurance, a military action overseas), and now we’re going to darn well sure to make a GOOD decision about it, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first admit, some decisions are certainly better than others, and many of the things I’ve written this post so far are about ways to maximize the chances of better decisions rather than worse ones. Yet, we significantly overestimate our ability to predict the outcomes of our decisions, while underestimating our cognitive biases and corruption by self-serving influence of special interests feeding those biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you may be familiar with the field of genetic algorithms (GA) – basically computer programs that randomly evolve offspring which compete to for better fitness for a solution to a problem. In many contexts, GAs &lt;a href=&quot;/human-competetive&quot;&gt;outperform human programmers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, agile/adaptive governance approaches outperform structures which focus heavily on the decision-making process. When we minimize the cost of trying something and learning from it, we’re leveraging human intelligence in the learning, rather than in predicting an unknown future. Those organizations also tend to have more fun, and much shorter meetings! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transparency-blockchain-will-save-us&quot;&gt;Transparency (Blockchain Will Save Us)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I favor transparency, and see a commitment to transparency as admirable. Yet transparency often doesn’t accomplish what we hope. In some cases, people feel &lt;a href=&quot;/geek-feminism/gittip-crisis&quot;&gt;vulnerable to attacks or persecution&lt;/a&gt; from disagreeing parties. In others, tension between personal inclinations and social pressures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the sticky point for me is that &lt;a href=&quot;/wikipedia/DIKW_pyramid&quot;&gt;data taken out of context is not information&lt;/a&gt;, it is misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have attained the level of expertise to be involved with making decisions about a complex issue, then you are using specialized language in your discourse which is inherently opaque to people outside. People outside of your context and domain of specialization can hear/see the same words, but they don’t have the same meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This inaccessible jargon is an unavoidable part of “compressing” the massive complexity of a problem into sentences we can actually speak. You could listen to recordings of MetaCurrency design conversations, but almost nobody would know what we’re saying. They might think they do, because we’re using familiar words, but we’ve refined their use in our context to have meanings others don’t share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as far as decision making goes, transparency doesn’t make that accessible in the ways we’d hope, and in fact can fuel massive misunderstanding or misinformation campaigns by taking things said out of context. But what about transparent recordkeeping on something like a blockchain?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, far as governance goes, &lt;a href=&quot;/metacurrency/cryptocurrencies-are-dead&quot;&gt;blockchain doesn’t have any&lt;/a&gt;. They skipped the step of building social processes for decision-making for changes to the underlying technology, so even the blockchain is vulnerable to all the challenges of human irrationality as it evolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is certainly a step in the right direction to establish open record-keeping with &lt;a href=&quot;/p2p-foundation/blockchains-major-design-flaw&quot;&gt;data integrity assured&lt;/a&gt; by cryptographic hashes, and &lt;a href=&quot;/ceptr/holochain&quot;&gt;data provenance verified&lt;/a&gt; by cryptographic signatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---As someone building blockchain alternatives, I'm biased, but I'm dubious about building governance on an architecture only decentralized not fully distributed. Also, forcing a single perspective to record as a global consensus involves significant loss of resolution, while requiring massive processing. (Sorry, blockchain geeks, I love you and what you're trying to do but think we have to take another approach.) --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-is-there-no-hope&quot;&gt;So, Is There No Hope?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If bankrupt assumptions are built into today’s governments and even most leading-edge digital governance tools, aren’t we screwed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. We’re in pretty good shape. The hidden benefit of the current crises happening in numerous governments is that people are loosening their irrational faith the system, and opening to new possibilities they couldn’t have considered even just a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, although this could all seem like discouraging news, to me it is heartening, because it means that gnawing desire we’ve had in our guts for something better, is justified. I can tell you, there are approaches to governance which are actually fun, easy, agile, and deeply satisfying. But we do have to confront the challenges of taking them to large scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s &lt;a href=&quot;/art-of-gov&quot;&gt;design them together&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post has gotten too long, so I’ll have to finish by making this a series of posts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Challenging Broken Assumptions&lt;/a&gt; of Governance (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Powerful Design Principles&lt;/a&gt; for Next-Gen Governance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Healthy Feedback Loops&lt;/a&gt;: The 90% of Governance Beyond Decision Making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/11/challenging-broken-assumptions-of-governance</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Art of Governance</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/01/art-of-governance</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;!-- TOC START min:1 max:3 link:true update:true --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#clarity-about-governance&quot;&gt;Clarity about Governance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-is-possible&quot;&gt;What is Possible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#healthy-feedback-loops-the-90-of-governance-beyond-decision-making&quot;&gt;Healthy Feedback Loops: The 90% of Governance Beyond Decision Making&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#humans-and-their-big-brains&quot;&gt;Humans and Their Big Brains&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-overwhelming-portion-of-governance&quot;&gt;The Overwhelming Portion of Governance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#flows-set-in-motion-stay-in-motion&quot;&gt;Flows Set in Motion Stay in Motion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#governance-is-much-more-than-decision-making&quot;&gt;Governance is much more than Decision Making&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- TOC END --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been a long-time intention to shift our focus toward better governance and collective intelligence AFTER addressing some fundamental infrastructure needed for it go well. Good governance infrastructure needs to be decentralized, interoperable, mashable into new workflows, quickly evolvable, and the tech for that hasn’t been quite ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I feel like we’re getting close enough with Ceptr that these capacities are just around the corner. So, although I’d like to wait till we have the tools ready, the rising buzz of energy that the Trump administration is triggering makes me feel like I have a responsibility to create a collaborative space for this work pronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clarity-about-governance&quot;&gt;Clarity about Governance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governance is not the same as a government. Government as we know it is a monolithic bureaucracy. And frankly, it isn’t very adept at governance – at least not as understood as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Governance has two faces:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managing continuity and coherence of healthy patterns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steering toward goals and away from dangers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; I talked about how those two faces have been falsely dichotomized into conservative and progressive candidates and platforms. This&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-possible&quot;&gt;What is Possible&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are understandably skeptical about utopian visions of what is possible given the gridlock and corruption we call politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;healthy-feedback-loops-the-90-of-governance-beyond-decision-making&quot;&gt;Healthy Feedback Loops: The 90% of Governance Beyond Decision Making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;humans-and-their-big-brains&quot;&gt;Humans and Their Big Brains&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As big-brained, symbol-using animals, we tend to over-value the importance of the tiny rational portion of ourselves. For example, we put kids in over 12 years of school which focuses on rational storage and retrieval of information in the mind. In school, most are never taught how to collaborate (It’s called cheating.), or how to listen compassionately, establish friendship or trust, express their deepest commitments (That stuff is all a distraction called “talking in class.”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry… I’m ranting. This isn’t about &lt;a href=&quot;/agile-learning-centers&quot;&gt;better alternatives to our broken educational system&lt;/a&gt;, it’s about our misplaced emphasis on rationality in our selves and our ideas of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See way back in the first post in this series, we identified problems with the assumption that humans are rational. And since most strategies for governance revolve around this false assumption it probably seemed like pretty bad news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s the good news, even though the decision-making part of governance receives most our attention in designing systems, it’s a tiny part of governance. Let’s be generous and call it 10% of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the other 90%?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-overwhelming-portion-of-governance&quot;&gt;The Overwhelming Portion of Governance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I defined &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;governance in the context of living systems&lt;/a&gt; as having two faces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preserving the integrity of what’s working, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving toward goals or away from dangers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making good decisions is almost completely about #2. I’m not saying it’s not important, but it is truthfully nowhere near as important as #1. Let’s look at why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the course of a day, the attention of your rational brain is mostly on #2: getting to work, accomplishing tasks, choosing what to eat, who to hang out with, etc. However, luckily for you, your autonomic system is doing most of the work: keeping you breathing, muscles contracting, heart pumping, feet walking, eyes scanning, even neurons learning new patterns of navigating your environment &lt;strong&gt;un&lt;/strong&gt;-consciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body is incredibly complex, it’s handling millions of interactions every moment, while your rational brain deals with one, maybe three. A social organism, such as a corporation, institution, or government, is fundamentally the same. The CEO is certainly not micro-managing every operation of the organism. If she is, then she’s probably not doing her job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flows-set-in-motion-stay-in-motion&quot;&gt;Flows Set in Motion Stay in Motion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, this isn’t necessarily true, but I like the sound it stated like &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Newtonian Physics&lt;/a&gt;. This is really the goal of building good self-regulating governance, establishing healthy patterns of flows that sustain themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;doesn’t happen just automatically, but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;governance-is-much-more-than-decision-making&quot;&gt;Governance is much more than Decision Making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are needs or problems identified, goals selected, dangers foreseen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are shared values identified, healthy patterns recognized and maintained?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is research conducted, information collected, evidence gathered?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End with teaser about upcoming currency design webinars&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/02/01/art-of-governance</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Future of Governance is not Governments</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2017/01/26/future-governance-is-not-governments</link>
				<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Living systems on every scale have &lt;strong&gt;governance&lt;/strong&gt; – methods of self-regulation to manage the coherence and continuity of the system. Also, for steering toward goals or away from dangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This governance is not the same as a government. Government as we know it is a blunt instrument designed to enforce the will of the many over the few (although at this point it enforces the will of few on the many) It is a monolithic bureaucracy. And frankly, it isn’t very good at governance, at least not as defined in the first paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-nature-of-change&quot;&gt;The Nature of Change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that governance includes both conserving continuity and making progress. All living systems have this tension between being conservative and progressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progressive:&lt;/strong&gt; Adapt or die – change is required. A system which cannot adapt to changing circumstances, will get steam-rolled by them. Furthermore, we want more than just adapting to survive, but evolving to improve and thrive. We want to move toward goals, and higher quality of life. And we want to be able perceive and avoid dangers, and respond deftly when confronted by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conservative:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintain integrity or fly apart. What makes a system work is the pattern of self-regulation it has established: feedback loops, dynamic balances, flows which nourish all the parts of whole, so the whole can function. Disruption of these integrity of these patterns brings death even more quickly than a failure to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;false-enemies&quot;&gt;False Enemies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globally, politics polarizes around that tension: conservative vs. progressive. This is a false choice. Both are mandatory. It doesn’t matter whether we like it or not. When the world around you is changing, and that change is accelerating, the question is never whether to change or stay the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The questions we must confront are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What changes are vital? (to survival and goals)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do we implement those changes in a way that doesn’t destroy the integrity of what works?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selecting a conservative vs. a progressive candidate is a false choice that we are forced to make because of broken architectures of governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-failure-of-representative-democracy&quot;&gt;The Failure of Representative Democracy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representative Democracy may have been a breakthrough 2000 years ago. It even made sense 200 years ago when the U.S. Constitution was written. The only way to discuss and deliberate was to go meet someplace, and everyone can’t ride hundreds of miles by horseback or carriage to participate, so you choose representatives to bring your local news and concerns to the table. There are many alternatives in an Internet age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fine – except for a few major problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One person can’t actually represent many.&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe if we sit down and you tell me your concerns and commitments about an issue, then I could represent you (and myself) on that issue. But as you add a few more people, that gets increasingly difficult. Now make it millions of people that I don’t talk to directly and make it apply across all issues. What are the chances I’m really representing you? Is it even possible that I could come close to representing that kind of population across the complex range of issues that officials are supposed to make decisions about?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Party Affiliation:&lt;/strong&gt; A two-party system reduces politics down to voting for a conservative or progressive. Multi-party politics isn’t much better as still reduces the range of discourse down to the ideological platform of the party. Voter choices go from 2 to 3 or 5, which is nowhere near the level of complexity of choice that we need for navigating the world we’re in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Local Issues:&lt;/strong&gt; Particularly, at the level of the Federal government, most of the decisions made have little to do with locale. Local decisions are certainly made on neighborhood, municipal, and loosely state levels. (Many states are too big be “local” ) So we are constrained to voting by party and locale. These factors map very poorly to the real world challenges we need to collectively navigate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-world-too-big-fast-and-complex&quot;&gt;A World too Big, Fast, and Complex&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Constitution was written for an Agrarian Republic. The level of complexity that officials were expected to confront absolutely did not include things like Nuclear Power and Weaponry, Electronic Surveillance, Climate Change, Net Neutrality, Air Traffic Control, etc. If you’ve gotten a glimpse of CSPAN, you probably have exposure to how poor a grasp politicians have on even basic workings of some of these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can’t be experts on everything, especially when their job security is mostly tied to schmoozing influential funders. We have politicians without the right expertise, with inherent conflicts of interest by who they have please to keep getting campaign funds, who can’t possibly represent the complexity of their constituency, and are elected by association with ideological simplifications … and we pretend there’s a chance of good governance from this setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Constitutional Government fared fairly well for nearly a hundred agrarian years. Yet as the country moved into a more industrial era, the government had no good way to integrate major shift in economic power. I would assert that the Civil War was a symptom of that failure to integrate the northern industrial and southern agrarian economic needs and patterns except by military force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this point, the U.S. Government appeared to continue on smoothly but increasingly became controlled by the banks and corporations of the industrial economy. As the U.S. economy has been transitioning into information age dynamics, it gets harder to even maintain the appearance of relevance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bureaucracy simply doesn’t have the throughput to keep up with the increased complexity of issues and the pace that the world is changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-end-of-old-world-order&quot;&gt;The End of Old World Order&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government was already dying. The gap between what it had become and what we need it to be was becoming intolerable for too many people. That is part of what enabled Trump to get his foot into the door of the presidency, and if his first week in office is any indication, his team will dismantle much, and quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not business as usual. They are not playing by the old rules. There is a good chance that they won’t acknowledge any established means of reclaiming the power they’ve seized. Not by impeachment. Not by the next election. Not by constitutional convention. Spending your energy on those things will likely be energy lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll see if I’m right about this, but if I am, that means our only real alternative is build the next generation of self-governance that reclaims the powers we’ve surrendered to the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will need to a P2P, fully-distributed, digital democracy that will be so different from how we think of government, that it may better be thought of as a kind of social network. You jump on, scan your feed, participate in conversations you’re interested in, weigh in with “likes” or other similar feedback, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feasibility&quot;&gt;Feasibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, the reality of this will sound far-fetched. Remember, the cells in our body figured out how to do extremely sophisticated self-governance on scales of trillions. Fully P2P governance. No cell is President or Dictator of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If cells can do it, we can too. Unfortunately, we don’t have millions of years to figure it out, we’ve escalated the situation to create the crises we needed to force our own hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying this kind of transition will be easy for people to accept. No change on this magnitude is easy. However, I don’t see any better alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;invitation&quot;&gt;Invitation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are agitated. Energy is emerging to connect for change. People need to be connecting and having new conversations about what to do. I’d like to channel some of that energy into building real alternatives instead of chasing expired political strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an invitation to all who have the capacities to contribute to building the world we need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Community organizers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social process wonks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programmers and Crypto geeks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UX, UI, and Graphic Designers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All people willing to leave old pictures of government behind and experiment with new self-governance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the technology side of things, please check out &lt;a href=&quot;/ceptr&quot;&gt;Ceptr&lt;/a&gt; and how you might be able to participate there. For the reinvention of governance, check out the &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/02/01/art-of-governance&quot;&gt;Art of Governance&lt;/a&gt; site I’m building this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Art of Governance, and the collaborative tools for sharing ideas and up-voting and such, will initially be on a normal (centralized) web site, but we’ll move it to fully-distributed tools as quickly as we are able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come play!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2017/01/26/future-governance-is-not-governments</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Ode to ELL and my Backlog</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2016/06/13/ode-to-ell-and-my-backlog</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Crap… it all got deleted and I have to re-write it.  Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2016/06/13/ode-to-ell-and-my-backlog</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Jerry Michalski interviews me about Alternative Currencies IFTF FutureCast Interview</title>
				<link>https://www.artbrock.com/2016/05/15/jerry-michalski-interviews-me-about-alternative-ccurrencies-iftf-futrecast-interview</link>
				<pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<description>
</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.artbrock.com/2016/05/15/jerry-michalski-interviews-me-about-alternative-ccurrencies-iftf-futrecast-interview</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
